<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>math on Patryk Węgrzyn</title><link>https://pwegrzyn.github.io/categories/math/</link><description>Recent content in math on Patryk Węgrzyn</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pwegrzyn.github.io/categories/math/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>On the (Un)reasonable Effectivness of Math in Physics</title><link>https://pwegrzyn.github.io/2022/on-the-unreasonable-effectivness-of-math/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pwegrzyn.github.io/2022/on-the-unreasonable-effectivness-of-math/</guid><description>In his famous 1960 article Eugene Wigner argued about the &amp;ldquo;the unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics in the natural sciences&amp;rdquo;. The main point made here was the existance of a seemingly unexpected natural relationship between math and physics. Specifically, why does math lend itself so well to modelling of physical reality? Why are physical laws and processess even expressable as mathematical equations in the first place? Where does this correspondence between abstract platonic ideas and concrete physical observations originate from?</description></item><item><title>Geometry is Everywhere: or How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Manifold</title><link>https://pwegrzyn.github.io/2021/differential-geometry-is-everywhere/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pwegrzyn.github.io/2021/differential-geometry-is-everywhere/</guid><description>When I was in high school, I was really into physics. Later, even though I chose to purse a degree in Computer Science, my love for physics did not go away. Quite the opposite, my math classes at uni allowed me to finally go deeper into more advanced physics topics (till then I had really only read the first tomes of Feynman&amp;rsquo;s lecture textbooks, GR and QM was beyond my skills at that period).</description></item><item><title>My New Favourite Math Abstraction - Lawvere's Fixed Point Theorem</title><link>https://pwegrzyn.github.io/2021/my-new-favourite-math-theorem/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pwegrzyn.github.io/2021/my-new-favourite-math-theorem/</guid><description>When someone&amp;rsquo;s asked to think about the most famous and revolutionary math ideas in recent centuries, there&amp;rsquo;s a high probability that they will think of either Cantor&amp;rsquo;s diagonal argument, proving that some infinities are bigger than others, or Gödel&amp;rsquo;s incompleteness theorem, which shows that a formal system can contain statements that are not provable within the system, or Russell&amp;rsquo;s paradox, which suggests that some sets are actually not allowed to exist, or Turing&amp;rsquo;s halting problem, which in essence proves that not all problems have an algorithmic solution.</description></item><item><title>The Single Most Valuable Math Book You Probably Haven't Heard About</title><link>https://pwegrzyn.github.io/2021/thinking-mathematically-review/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pwegrzyn.github.io/2021/thinking-mathematically-review/</guid><description>Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve had the pleasure of reading &amp;ldquo;Thinking mathematically&amp;rdquo; by J. Mason, L. Burton and K. Stacey. The book has been recommended to me in a random Twitter conversation and since I haven&amp;rsquo;t really heard about it before (nor had I any familiarity with its authors) I decided to push in on top of my reading list out of sheer curiosity regarding its praising reviews. And oh boy, was I not disappointed!</description></item></channel></rss>